http://www.health.vic.gov.au/privacy

Site Navigation
Page Content
Our websites
Better Health Channel
Health and medical information for consumers, quality assured by the Victorian government
DHHS
A gateway to the strategies, policies, programs and services delivered by the Department of Health & Human Services.
Seniors Online
Victorian government portal for older people, with information about government and community services and programs.
Search
Type a minimum of three characters then press UP or DOWN on the keyboard to navigate the autocompleted search results
Design resources for private health service establishments
Professional standards in private health service establishments
Legislation updates for private health service establishments
Complaints about private health service establishments
Cosmetic procedures
Forms, checklists and guidelines for private health service establishments
Maternal and Child Health Service resources
Maternal and Child Health Workforce professional development
health-practitioners
Licences and permits to possess (& possibly supply) scheduled substances
Suicide prevention in Victoria
Improving mental health outcomes for culturally and linguistically diverse communities
Victoria’s 10-year mental health plan
Renewal grants for mental health and alcohol and other drug facilities
leadership
Victoria's clinical supervision framework for mental health nurses
the-mental-health-workforce-reference-group
The Centre for Mental Health Workforce Learning and Development
aod-performance-management-framework
Alcohol and Other Drug Residential Rehabilitation Facility Design Guidelines
Drug alerts
Green ‘UPS’ pills containing N-ethylpentylone (no MDMA)
COVID Safe AOD funding grants – guidelines and application form
Public hospitals in Victoria
A list of public hospitals and health services in Victoria.
Patient care
The Victorian healthcare system focuses on providing patient-centered care that is timely, appropriate and effective.
Integrated care
Integration is the provision of well-connected, effective and efficient care that takes account of and is organised around a person’s health and social needs.
Quality, safety and service improvement
Victorian health services aim to meet or exceed quality and safety standards to ensure our health sector provides world-class care.
Rural health
The Victorian Government is working to improve access to quality healthcare in rural Victoria.
Private health service establishments
Private hospitals, day procedure centres and mobile health services in Victoria must be registered and comply with regulations on patient safety and care
Boards and governance
Victorian health service boards have well defined responsibilities and the department acknowledges board education as a crucial activity.
Data, reporting and analytics
The Department of Health & Human Services manages Victorian health data collections by providing standards, specifications and quality processes.
Funding, performance and accountability
The Victorian Government plans, develops policy, regulates and funds over 500 health services and organisations.
Patient fees and charges
Patient fees chargeable for admitted and non-admitted services in Victoria's public healthcare services.
Financial accounting and policy
Information and resources to support public hospitals and health services to report their financial data to the department.
Planning and infrastructure
Victorian health service providers are adopting leading-edge systems and technologies to help ensure that our health system delivers world-class care.
Popular items
Maternity record order form
Safer Care Victoria
Victorian Agency for Health Information
Close Menu (This link is for visual users only)
Primary & community health
Primary & community health
Primary care
Information about primary care, working with general practice and private providers including Emergency Response planning, Primary Care Partnerships and Health Condition Support Grants service.
Integrated care
Information about delivering care that crosses the boundaries between primary, community, acute health and social care, including the Bilateral Agreement on Coordinated Care, HealthLinks: Chronic Care, the Chronic Care Guide, and service coordination practice.
Community health
Information about Victoria’s community health services, including registration and governance, the Community Health Program, demand management, service improvement and services targeted at population groups at risk of poorer health outcomes.
Dental health
Information about public dental care in Victoria, including eligibility and access, fees, waiting lists, and data reporting.
Maternal and Child Health Service
Information about the Victorian Maternal and Child Health (MCH) Service, including professional development information, resources, reporting data and the MCH framework.
Funding model review
We are reviewing the pricing and funding model for the Public Dental Program and the Community Health Program.
Close Menu (This link is for visual users only)
Public health
Public health
Cemeteries
Information about public cemeteries, crematoria and cemetery trusts in Victoria for various stakeholders.
Medicines and poisons
Victorian legislation ensures that medicines and poisons are used safely. Healthcare professionals must be aware of the relevant laws for their occupation.
Environmental health
In Victoria, the department has an important role in protecting the health of Victorians from the potential health effects of environmental hazards.
Food safety
All Victorian food businesses must follow the food safety regulations for their class of food premises.
Immunisation
Victorian information about vaccination for children, adolescents and adults.
Infectious diseases
Guidelines and advice for health professionals about infectious diseases.
Population health
Evidence gathering, statistical data and evaluations are important tools for planning preventative health and wellbeing measures.
Population screening
Screening programs include the national cervical, breast and bowel cancer screening programs, newborn bloodspot screening, prenatal screening and infant hearing screening.
Preventive health
Disease prevention and early detection targeting specific areas such as obesity, physical activity, sexual health and heart disease.
Radiation
The department administers the Radiation Act 2005. Users and managers of radiation practices are licensed under this Act.
Tobacco reforms
Anti-smoking laws and policies have contributed to a continuing decline of smoking rates across Victoria.
Water
The department protects the public by safeguarding drinking water, facilitating the safe use of alternative water supplies and ensuring healthy swimming.
Popular items
Seasonal influenza 2019
Chief Health Officer
Cemeteries and fees search
Notify infectious disease
Anaphylaxis notifications
Close Menu (This link is for visual users only)
Mental health
Mental health
Mental health services
GPs and primary carers provide most mental health services. Specialist services are also available.
National suicide prevention implementation strategy
As one part of making suicide prevention a priority, all governments have committed to drafting a new national suicide prevention strategy for Australia: the National suicide prevention implementation strategy. This strategy will embody the collective aspiration of all governments that fewer lives are lost to suicide and will be supported by every health minister in Australia.
Practice and service quality
Victoria’s public mental health services are committed to high standards of practice and service.
Mental health consumers and carers
Consumers and carers play a critical role in the delivery of mental health services in Victoria.
Prevention and promotion
In Victoria the promotion of mental health and wellbeing is a priority.
Priorities and transformation
Victoria is committed to providing world-leading standards of care for all people living with a mental illness.
Rights and advocacy
The Mental Health Act 2014 supports advocacy, diversity, privacy and complaints processes.
Chief Mental Health Nurse
Victoria's Chief Mental Health Nurse provides leadership in the mental health nursing sector
Research and reporting
Reporting requirements for Victorian public mental health services and an overview of government-funded mental health research.
Hello open minds
A career in mental health has rewards for everyone.
Order mental health publications
A hard copy of a publication can be ordered online by filling out this form - we do not ship outside of Australia. Some items are available in limited quantities only.
Close Menu (This link is for visual users only)
Alcohol & drugs
Alcohol & drugs
AOD treatment services
Victoria’s specialist alcohol and other drug treatment services cover a broad spectrum of community-based and residential treatment options.
AOD policy, research and legislation
This webpage links to more information from the Victorian Government about policy, research and legislation for the alcohol and other drug sector.
AOD standards and guidelines
Standards and guidelines direct alcohol and other drug service providers to ensure safe, accessible and professional treatment services.
AOD workforce
The Victorian alcohol and other drug treatment services workforce operates in a complex environment. The government is supporting the sector to meet these challenges.
AOD Careers - Welcome to a world of difference
The Alcohol & Other Drugs (AOD) sector is growing, with additional funding opening up diverse job opportunities across a range of programs and settings.
With so many different jobs available, we’re after lots of different people. Do you have what it takes?
Drug policy and services newsletters
Drug policy and services newsletters, covering topics such as the National Ice Taskforce, the 10 year mental health plan, and sector engagement.
Funding and reporting for AOD
This section provides information about funding models for alcohol and other drug service providers and details about the reporting requirements.
Drug alerts
Information about high-risk drug products that may be circulating in Victoria.
COVID Safe AOD funding grants – guidelines and application form
Information about high-risk drug products that may be circulating in Victoria.
Close Menu (This link is for visual users only)
Ageing & aged care
Ageing & aged care
Supporting independent living
The Victorian Government supports older Victorians to live independently in the community through a range of support programs.
Supported residential services
Supported residential services provide accommodation and support services for Victorians who need help with everyday activities. They are regulated by the Victorian Government.
Residential aged care services
Residential aged care is for older people who can no longer live at home. These services are funded and regulated by the Commonwealth Government and can be operated by not-for-profit, private or state government providers.
My Aged Care assessment services
Assessment services help older people and their carers to identify care that best meets their needs and access Commonwealth Government services for older people.
Home and Community Care in Victoria
The Home and Community Care Program for Younger People provides funding for services which support frail older people, younger people with disabilities and their carers.
Wellbeing and participation
The Victorian Government provides a range of programs to maximise older people’s health and wellbeing and social participation across all life stages.
Dementia-friendly environments
A Victorian government resource providing information and advice on designing and caring for people with dementia in residential aged care settings.
Close Menu (This link is for visual users only)
Back to
Home
Home
Privacy
Privacy
Share (show more)
Listen (show more)
Listen
More (show more)
Email
Print
The Privacy and Data Protection Act 2014 and the Health Records Act 2001 regulate the information handling of personal and health information. It includes standards for information collection, storage, access, transmission, disclosure, use and disposal.
The Complaints, Integrity and Privacy Unit (CIPu) supports department and funded agency compliance with information privacy legislation. CIPu provides advice, training and tools to support privacy compliance and promote best practice within the department and public agencies. CIPu are also responsible for coordinating the department's response to privacy complaints.
Privacy policy
The Department of Health and Human Services is committed to protecting the privacy of personal information which we and our funded service partners handle. Personal information is information which directly or indirectly identifies a person.
We collect and handle a range of personal information for the purposes of providing services or to carry out our statutory functions. We also collect some personal information for planning, funding, monitoring and evaluating our services and functions, but where practicable we remove identifying details from information used for these purposes.
In accordance with our responsibilities, the services and functions which we and our service partners provide relate primarily to the areas of health, community support and the protection of public health and safety. They include in particular primary and community health, public hospitals, mental health, disability, family support, child protection, youth justice, housing, homelessness support, and public health. We are committed to providing coordinated care to our clients.
We recognise that the nature of these services means that much of the information we handle is particularly sensitive.
We recognise that privacy principles protect personal information both as a matter of individual right, and to support the public interest in ensuring government can collect information necessary for its services.
We recognise the essential right of individuals to have their information handled in ways which they would reasonably expect protected on the one hand, and made accessible to them on the other.
These privacy values are reflected in and supported by our corporate values: collaborative relationships, professional integrity and respect, quality, responsibility and client focus.
We are bound by the Victorian privacy laws, the Privacy and Data Protection Act 2014 and the Health Records Act 2001, as well as other laws which impose specific obligations in regard to handling information.
We have adopted the respective Privacy Principles contained in the Victorian privacy laws as minimum standards in relation to handling personal information.
In broad terms this means that we:
collect only information which we need for a specified primary purpose
ensure that the person knows why we collect it and how we will handle it
use and disclose it only for the primary or a directly related purpose, or for another purpose with the persons consent (unless otherwise authorised by law)
store it securely, protecting it from unauthorised access
retain it for the period authorised by the Public Records Act 1973
provide the person with access to their own information, and the right to seek its correction.
For information in our possession, this right is available through the Freedom of Information Act 1982. See Freedom of Information for more.
For information in the possession of our service partners, this right is available through privacy legislation.
This policy is complemented by high-level departmental guidelines intended to assist the department and its funded service partners to put the policy and law into practice.
Sizmek Pixel
This website may from time to time use a Sizmek Pixel. We use this tool only on specific marketing landing pages. This tool allows us to assess the effectiveness of digital advertising for public health campaigns.
The collected data is anonymous and Better Health Channel cannot see the personal data of any individual user.
For more information visit the privacy policy section of the Sizmek website.
For Sizmek opt-out options, see opt-out options and additional information.
Privacy principles
Key privacy principles in summary
Health Privacy Principles (HPP)
Collection - Only collect health information if necessary for the performance of a function or activity and with consent (or if it falls within HPP 1). Notify individuals about what you do with the information and that they can gain access to it.
Use and disclosure - Only use or disclose health information for the primary purpose for which it was collected or a directly related secondary purpose the person would reasonably expect. Otherwise, you generally need consent.
Data quality - Take reasonable steps to ensure health information you hold is accurate, complete, up-to-date and relevant to the functions you perform.
Data security and retention - Safeguard the health information you hold against misuse, loss, unauthorised access and modification. Only destroy or delete health information in accordance with HPP 4.
Openness - Document clearly expressed policies on your management of health information and make this statement available to anyone who asks for it.
Access and correction - Individuals have a right to seek access to health information held about them in the private sector, and to correct it if it is inaccurate, incomplete, misleading or not up-to-date.*
Identifiers - Only assign a number to identify a person if the assignment is reasonably necessary to carry out your functions efficiently.
Anonymity - Give individuals the option of not identifying themselves when entering transactions with organisations where this is lawful and practicable.
Transborder data flows - Only transfer health information outside Victoria if the organisation receiving it is subject to laws substantially similar to the HPPs.
Transfer/closure of practice of health service provider - If you're a health service provider, and your business or practice is being sold, transferred or closed down, without you continuing to provide services, you must give notice of the transfer or closure to past service users.
Making information available to another health service provider - If you're a health service provider, you must make health information relating to an individual available to another health service provider if requested by the individual.
Information Privacy Principles (IPP)
Collection - Collect only personal information that is necessary for performance of functions. Advise individuals that they can gain access to personal information.
Use and disclosure - Use and disclose personal information only for the primary purpose for which it was collected or a secondary purpose the person would reasonably expect. Use for secondary purposes should have the consent of the person.
Data quality - Make sure personal information is accurate, complete and up-to-date.
Data security - Take reasonable steps to protect personal information from misuse, loss, unauthorised access, modification or disclosure.
Openness - Document clearly expressed policies on management of personal information and provide the policies to anyone who asks.
Access and correction - Individuals have a right to seek access to their personal information and make corrections. Access and correction will be handled mostly under the Victorian Freedom of Information Act.
Unique identifiers - A unique identifier is usually a number assigned to an individual in order to identify the person for the purposes of the organisations operations. Tax File Numbers and Drivers Licence Numbers are examples. Unique identifiers can facilitate data matching. Data matching can diminish privacy. IPP 7 limits the adoption and sharing of unique numbers.
Anonymity - Give individuals the option of not identifying themselves when entering transactions with organisations if that would be lawful and feasible.
Transborder data flows - Basically, if your personal information travels, your privacy protection should travel with it. Transfer of personal information outside Victoria is restricted. Personal information may be transferred only if the recipient protects privacy under standards similar to Victorias IPPs.
Sensitive information - The law restricts collection of sensitive information like an Individuals racial or ethnic origin, political views, religious beliefs, sexual preferences, membership of groups or criminal record.
Website privacy statement
See the Website privacy statement for information about how any personal information about you will be treated as you access and interact with this website.
Relevant legislation
The Victorian Legislation website provides free access to all relevant Acts and Regulations.
Search for the following:
Freedom of Information Act 1982
Ombudsman Act 1973
Privacy and Data Protection Act 2014
Health Records Act 2001
Whistleblowers Protection Act 2001
Whistleblowers Protection Regulations 2001
Financial Management Act 1994
Charter of Human Rights and Responsibilities Act 2006
Disability Act 2006.
In this topic
Website privacy
Freedom of Information
Copyright
Disclaimer
Accessibility
More information
Office for the Commissioner for Privacy and Data Protection
Victorian Legislation
Provides free access to all relevant Acts and Regulations
Contact details
Department of Health & Human Services
Senior Privacy Advisor
For further information on how the Department manages privacy please use these contact details. Postal address: GPO Box 4057, Melbourne, Victoria 3001.
Email:privacy@dhhs.vic.gov.au
Topics
Ageing and aged care
Alcohol & other drugs
Emergencies
Hospitals and health services
Mental health
Primary and community health
This web site is managed and authorised by the Department of Health & Human Services, State Government of Victoria, Australia
© Copyright State of Victoria 2017-2020
